Guide to the Dante Gabriel Rossetti Letters to Ellen Heaton
Yale Center for British Art, Rare Books and Manuscripts
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 October 16; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.138)
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Ashburton, Louisa, Lady, 1827-1903; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 October 28; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (3 pages): autograph letter signed; 19 x 23 cm, folded to 19 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.150)
  Rossetti will send Heaton's Sir Galahad today. He asks Heaton not to tell anyone the price of the Joan of Arc as "it would have been considerably higher had it been sold when finished instead of by commission.". Rossetti states that the letter Heaton mentioned in a previous letter is a Whistler and the one signed "Ned" is a Jones and mentions that he had asked Christina Rossetti to describe them to Heaton. He ends: "Lady Ashburton has not gone fasting through the fact of my artistic provender here being all bespoke. She has given me several commissions, one being a small Joan of Arc."
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Ashburton, Louisa, Lady, 1827-1903; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1864 November 13; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (1 page): autograph letter signed; 21 x 27 cm, folded to 21 x 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 64.155)
  "Your letter has been sent on to me here. I expect to be back in another week or so. I am much pleased that the Joan of Arc pleases you. There is no alteration whatsoever in the Sir Galahad. The Joan was painted from a female model, and looks like nothing in the world but a female."
  Addressed from Paris.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. How Sir Galahad, Sir Bors and Sir Percival were fed with the Sanct Grael; but Sir Percival's sister died by the way; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Joan of Arc; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1868 January 9; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter; 18 x 21 cm, folded to 18 x 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 68.4)
  Rossetti tells Heaton that it is "against [his] interests" to exhibit his work at present, unless it is work "of great importance." "I hold a fortunate position at present in possessing a market unassailable by incompetence, ill-will, or to put it in its mildest and frequently true form, by mere diversity of taste. You will greatly oblige me therefore by declining to send anything of mine; and indeed I have lately made the stipulation, when parting with works, that they are not to be exhibited without my consent." The paper has been trimmed on the third and fourth pages, with partial loss of content. Rossetti is apparently asking Heaton if she could loan him one of his works commissioned by her -- perhaps Dante's dream -- to help him in working on a new piece. Rossetti offers to produce a sketch for Heaton in exchange for the loan.
  Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882. Dante's dream at the time of the death of Beatrice; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Exhibitions; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882 -- Correspondence; Heaton, Ellen, 1816-1894 -- Correspondence
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1869 January 25; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 1 folded sheet (4 pages): autograph letter signed; 18 x 23 cm, folded to 18 x 12 cm (Box 1, Folder 69.11)
  With envelope. Letterhead: 16 Cheyne Walk, Chelsea.
  Rossetti acknowledges Heaton's hesitance to lend him Dante's dream in their previous correspondence (see letter dated 9 January 1868) because she wanted to show it to visitors at the Leeds Exhibition. As the exhibition is now finished, Rossetti asks if she will now loan him the work. Rossetti says he would have needed it before now but he recently had to suspend all his work due to the "troublesome state of [his] eyesight". Now that he is working again, Rossetti expresses the pressing need to have Dante's dream to begin his new pieice.
- Dante Gabriel Rossetti letter to Ellen Heaton, 1875 October 9?; Rossetti, Dante Gabriel, 1828-1882; 3 letter signature fragments: autograph letters signed; 9 x 12 cm and smaller (Box 1, Folder misc.1)
  With envelope. Sent from 14 Chantham Place, Blackfriars.
  These fragments are examples of Rossetti's letter closings. They read: "Believe me, dear Miss Heaton, Yours ever truly, D. G. Rossetti"; "Very truly yours, D. G. Rossetti"; and "Yours sincerely, D. G. Rossetti."